Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade
鹊桥小队翻译组 https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
The past few days have been hot.
I heard from your nursemaid
that you have stayed up late studying every night.
Diligence is one thing -
but you must also take care of your health.
Mother, you had refreshments sent to me every night.
I don't feel tired.
The refreshments are meant as a reminder
that it is time to rest,
rather than continuing your hard work.
I misunderstood.
Peace to Noble Consort Lumière, and the Fourth Prince.
- The night is cold and windy...
- Your Highness.
Why are you standing here alone?
His Majesty ordered me to come,
but the Third Prince is inside right now.
Mr. Su informed me that His Majesty is angered
and told me to wait outside for now.
I told you to recite Wei Zheng's
“Ten Recommendations to Emperor Taizong”.
You recited it with no hesitation.
But when I asked you
how Taizong managed to "rule with a light hand,"
you faltered and couldn't give a clear answer.
Haven't you already learned from your shifu
about the "benevolent rule" of Taizong?
I've... I've learned the "Zhenguan Zhengyao"...
Im... Imperial Mother told me to read it thoroughly.
Your shifu and Imperial Mother are very diligent.
But you are flippant and feckless!
You began your studies at the age of five.
More than a decade has since passed.
I don't know where all those years of studies have gone.
I remember two years ago, you could recite most of "Zhenguan Zhengyao."
But now you've forgotten everything!
It's fortunate that your shifu has a good temper.
If I were to teach you,
watching you study for a day would have killed me.
Imperial Father, please calm your anger.
Calm my anger? I wish I could!
But you don't allow me half a second of peace.
You are my eldest son.
I don't expect you to achieve greatness or to share my burden.
I only hope that you can be a good role model for your younger brothers,
so I have less to worry about.
But you persist in behaving like you're good for nothing!
His Majesty is so enraged.
His Majesty is the Son of Heaven.
He cannot be as mild-tempered or carefree as His Lordship.
His Lordship doesn't have children yet.
But if he does someday,
he might be even stricter than His Majesty
out of earnest paternal love.
By the way, Fourth Prince,
I heard that you have been studying rigorously.
Are you able to recite the books His Majesty mentioned?
I can't compare to my third brother.
I started my studies later than he did.
Your Highness said I study hard -
that's because I'm dull-witted.
I must spend more time studying
or else I will be scolded by my shifu.
Read and comprehend the essay within the next three days!
Don't come see me again
if you cannot grasp its content!
Greetings to Consort Lumière, and to Concubine Paix.
You should go inside now.
His Majesty was in an ireful mood.
His words were harsher than usual.
Don't take them to heart.
You are his son after all.
All will be well in a few days.
Yes, I thank Your Highness for your caring words.
You still need to return to your estate.
Go ahead.
Imperial Mother is waiting to go over my studies at her palace.
It's already so late.
At what time will you rise for class tomorrow?
At a quarter to four.
Do you sleep so few hours every day?
Imperial Mother says: "A clumsy bird needs to fly early."
I'm not as clever as others,
so I must be more diligent than them.
That's why I must study hard day and night.
The Empress wants you to nurture your ambitions.
But you also ought to take care of yourself.
I heard your Imperial Father has
started selecting a wife for you.
It's good to start your family early
so you will have someone to look after you.
Yes.
It's quite late, please allow me to take my leave.
Mother, you see how hardworking my third brother is.
I must work harder than him
so that Imperial Father will be fond of me.
You just told Concubine Paix
that you haven't memorized all the essays His Majesty mentioned.
But a few days back, I heard you recite them fluently
and your comprehension was profound.
Mother, I've observed how you keep a low profile.
"My eyes and ears have been immersed,"
so I understand what I should do.
You are smart.
Mother and son "share the same pulse."
Of course I'm like you.
Mother, my third brother is the eldest son.
Will he become the Emperor?
I don't know.
But my sixth brother was born to you
and Imperial Father adores him the most.
So he will be crowned.
As long as my sixth brother becomes the Emperor,
I will be happy.
Your sixth brother is still young,
and I don't wish for him to be the emperor.
Only the most worthy of all
is capable of ruling the Empire.
Do you understand?
Yes.
Hongshi, do any of these ladies catch your eye?
Mother, you're benevolent to ask.
Allow me to obey your decision.
Choose whomever you prefer
and inform your Imperial Father yourself.
You've grown up.
I will only make arrangements
and not decisions for you.
Greetings, Your Highness.
Peace to Noble Consort Lumière.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
You all may rise.
I thank Your Noble Highness.
This is the first time we meet
and perhaps the first of many.
The Third Prince has grown taller.
The weather is pleasantly cooler today.
I invited you and Noble Consort Estime
to aid in choosing exceptional young ladies.
Every one of them looks perfect to me!
Take your time -
you'll find the outstanding one.
Her Majesty invited us here
so we can chime in with our support
if the Third Prince has a preference.
She doesn't want others to think
she made the decision on her own;
it will look like we all approve.
Who is in the Empress's favor?
Her own niece.
The one dressed in green. Her name is Qingying.
Qingying, come over and greet the Third Prince.
Yes.
Greetings, Third Prince.
This is my cousin's youngest daughter.
You can call her your cousin.
Cousin.
Third Prince, my maiden name is Qingying.
These flowers are just as pretty as the peonies
in Imperial Mother's palace.
Thank you for the kind words, Princess.
Longyue, come here.
Longyue, the myrtle trees over there are blooming.
- How about we go check them out?
- Hmm, yes.
The myrtle flowers are the finest in my palace.
You may all view them as you please.
We take our leave, Your Majesty.
Prince, I heard you like gingered plums,
may I offer you some?
Oh these plums?
It's not that I particularly like them.
Imperial Mother says that
plums stimulate the appetite, and ginger warms the Stomach,
so she encourages me to have them.
Her Majesty truly cares about your well-being, Prince.
You ought to follow Her Majesty's advice.
You don't seem to like children, do you?
Children are naughty and careless.
Grown-ups shouldn't mind their mistakes.
We don't need to pay attention to them.
I had this dress made especially for meeting you, Prince.
How could I let someone damage it?
I see. Longyue, come here.
Here’s your favorite, gingered plums.
They’re all yours.
Third Brother, you are the best to me!
Enjoy!
Longyue, let’s go. I’ll take you to see the flowers.
Perhaps the young people are feeling
a bit inhibited because of our presence.
It's getting windy.
Noble Consort Lumière, I’ll return and get changed.
I can’t find Mother!
Will Your Highness help me look for her?
Go ahead.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
I'm here!
How did you leave the garden without notice.
Fortunately, the Empress didn't fault you for that.
She isn't thinking of that now;
she’s too engrossed in the glory and wealth
of her Ula-Nara clan.
She doesn't care what we do.
You looked so bored sitting there.
So I came up with an excuse for Longyue to get you out.
Just look at those young ladies.
Each one is remarkable.
But the Third Prince seems indifferent.
That's true.
Longyue, your third brother looks dispirited.
Go ask him to join us.
Invite him to take a walk and relax.
Hurry.
Third brother, why don't you like those pretty girls?
I don’t like conceited women.
Or pretentious women.
Me too. I don’t like such women, either.
Then, what kind of women do you like?
Gentle... and serene.
You think I’m too much of a chatterbox?
Not at all. You’re most adorable!
Why has this flower changed color?
Mother brought me here this morning.
This flower is called “a beauty's visage”.
It is red at sunrise and turns pink when the sun sets.
The color is as fleeting as the expressions on a beauty's face.
Laughing or frowning as her mood changes.
This sister in front of us has the “visage of a beauty”.
Third brother, don't you think so?
"The renowned peony mudan, paired with
her beauty which could topple a nation."
Princess, I don't deserve being called "sister."
I am Noble Lady Lustré.
Noble Lady Lustré? How is it I’ve never met you?
And you are…?
This is my third brother.
Peace to the Third Prince.
Third brother, Noble Lady Lustré counts as one of our mothers.
You hardly visit the harem.
That's why you don’t know her.
Peace to Your Highness.
Peace to third brother, peace to Your Highness.
Peace to everyone!
Your Highness seems pensive, contemplating the flowers alone.
I was just thinking of my family at home.
They can’t come visit you in the palace?
It's a short reunion, and then more time apart.
My birth mother passed away.
I can't see her even if I wanted to.
Prince, please don’t have a heavy heart.
Although your birth mother is no longer here,
she is still watching over you wherever you are.
And all her actions in her life
would have been done for your benefit.
I thank Your Highness for such a thoughtful perspective.
Why is Your Highness unattended by a servant?
What difference would a servant make?
Having a companion who doesn’t understand you
is no better than being alone.
It's true. Sometimes it seems there would be comfort in a crowd
but often,
the bigger the crowd, the lonlier one can feel.
You're right about that, Prince.
It’s getting late. Allow me to take my leave.
One can be lonely however many companions there are.
Only a true confidante's companionship
can bring happiness.
What are you mumbling, third brother?
It's nothing. Let’s go.
Imperial Noble Consort is the best pipa player in the entire palace.
Noble Consort Lumière is the best on the qin zither.
But on the zheng zither, you are the best.
My slight skills can't compare with Their Highnesses'.
You have a calm nature and never vie for favor.
You certainly have your good qualities.
Your Majesty, the Third Prince is here.
Show him in.
Yes.
Your Majesty, I shall take my leave.
No need to leave. You're his elder.
Peace to Imperial Father.
What brings you here at this hour?
Have you finished reviewing your schoolwork?
Yes. I’ve reviewed all of it.
I also studied the essays that were covered in class.
That’s good.
I’ll quiz you on it another day.
Imperial Father,
actually, I'm here about my schooling.
I would like to ask for your permission.
Go ahead.
Imperial Father and Mother think I've grown up
and that it's time I establish a family.
But I think I should prioritize my studies right now,
instead of indulging myself in affairs of the heart.
So I'd rather not get married yet.
Your mother and I had the intention
to find someone to look after you.
I’m already well looked after by my servants.
Having a wife will inevitably distract me from my studies.
I know that I am too incompetent to share
any of your burdens, Imperial Father.
So I aspire to stay dedicated and not worry you.
I am relieved you think this way.
This was your Imperial Mother’s idea in the first place.
I’m in no hurry for you to wed.
Imperial Father, I hope I'll marry
a virtuous and gentle wife one day.
Indeed. Marital harmony matters the most.
You may leave now.
Yes.
Noble Lady Lustré plays the zheng as if
"chiming the Kunlun Mountains jade,"
or "the drip of dew onto lotus flowers."
I admire Your Higness's talent.
Thank you for the compliment, Third Prince.
You have a good ear.
"High Mountain and Flowing Water"
is Noble Lady Lustré's best piece.
Go on.
Yes.
Madam Autumn, please stay.
Please wait, My Lady.
What is it, Madam?
Although you can't become the primary wife right now,
Her Majesty had a valid point.
Why don't you set aside concern for the title,
and for now, serve the Third Prince as his concubine?
You can then be promoted later.
My aunt's lowest title was still Lord Consort.
Now she wants me to be just a titleless concubine?
I can see how much she cares for me!
You should think long-term, My Lady.
"Endure the indignity and carry the heaviness."
Endure the indignity?
Haven't I endured enough humiliation already?
The Third Prince doesn't cast his eyes on me.
Even His Majesty agrees the Third Prince won't be selecting a wife.
I'm already the laughingstock of the palace.
Should I shamelessly shove my face in his?
Then how would I be seen?
Please tell my aunt how thankful I am
for her generous condiseration.
Take care, My Lady.
Your Majesty.
Has she been sent off?
Yes. Lady Qingying wasn't happy.
Did you convey my message?
Yes, but My Lady Qingying was too high-minded to comply.
She's still young, and impetuous.
It wouldn't matter now if she is the wife or a concubine.
Once the Third Prince succeeds to the throne,
I will become the Empress Dowager.
It will be up to me to decide who is the next Empress.
The Empress must come from the Ula-Nara family.
Your Majesty is correct.
Lady Qingying is still too young to understand this.
What a shame she wouldn't comply.
The Ula-Nara family does not lack suitable girls.
Once the younger ones grow old enough,
there will be no place for her here.
It's because she doesn't appreciate Your Majesty's favor.
She even dared to remark on the fact that
Your Majesty was once a lord consort.
Very well.
Since she likes to speak of my lord consortship,
and also despises becoming a concubine,
then I will help her out once more.
She will learn that being the lord consort of another prince
cannot compare to being a concubine of the Third Prince.
Your Majesty means...
The Fourth Prince has turned sixteen.
I will go and ask His Majesty
to betroth Qingying to the Fourth Prince as his lord consort.
Isn't that too flattering for the Fourth Prince?
Flattering?
The Fourth Prince gets the Third Prince's cast-off.
And Noble Consort Lumière is not on good terms with me.
Gaining such a daughter-in-law
will cause only trouble for her.
Your Highness has a discerning mind.
But there is one thing I don't understand.
The imperial court has already raised
the need to establish a crown prince.
Why did Your Majesty encourage them
to suggest the Sixth Prince?
His Majesty is distrustful.
Any collusion between the court and the harem
is strictly prohibited.
We must often remind His Majesty of who is colluding.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
These past few years, I feel my health is nowhere near what it was.
The Empress wanted to find a wife for Hongshi,
and again, the imperial court brought up choosing a crown prince.
You have no idea how fed up I am.
Do all these officials think that I'm already so old
that I must choose a crown prince now?
Si Lang, you are in your prime years.
There's no rush to name a crown prince.
The Third Prince is promising but he needs more experience.
The court officials are simply concerned about how hard you work.
They just wish someone could share the weight you carry.
Even if I am to choose a crown prince,
I want to wait for the Sixth Prince to grow up.
Instead of worrying about what they should,
they worry over things they shouldn't.
Speaking of which, the Fourth Prince has turned sixteen.
Speaking of the Third Prince's marriage
also has me thinking of the Fourth Prince's.
Don't play favorites, Your Majesty.
You and the Empress are of the same mind.
The Empress has brought up her niece Qingying.
She wants to betroth her to Hongli.
Her Majesty is not being fair -
shoving her to the Fourth Prince
because the Third Prince doesn't like her.
Your Majesty said you had your eye on a girl surnamed Fuca,
daughter of Chahar's General Li.
An emperor cannot take back his words.
I know you also like Fuca.
Although she is a year younger than Hongli,
she has a stable personality.
But the Empress said Qingying only wants the title of Lord Consort.
Her request is a modest one so I didn't refuse it.
The Ula-Nara clan is a prominent lineage.
I'm afraid Her Majesty's niece will feel aggrieved at this title.
The Empress was disposed towards it.
I will not make her lose face.
Just as well. The Fourth Prince benefits from this after all.
The weather is lovely today. Let's go for a stroll.
If we stay inside every day, we'll grow moldy before long!
It's already September.
Did you have your servants collect willow branches for you?
What for?
"Willow" sounds like "stay", and the "ninth" month sounds like "long."
It is a wish for His Majesty to "stay long" in your palace.
I don't believe in that kind of thing.
You're currently in favor,
that's why you don't believe in it!
Isn't that His Lordship?
Noble Prince Guo.
It's been so long since I last saw Your Lordship.
Since Your Lordship got married,
you can't be as carefree as in the past.
With one lord consort on the left and another on the right,
Your Lordship cannot escape even with wings!
Your Noble Highness is always so humorous.
It's been a long time.
Noble Consort Lumière, have you been well?
I thank Your Lordship for asking.
I'm in good health.
What brings Your Lordship to the palace today?
I'm here to pay my respects to His Majesty.
It's windy. Please put on your cloak, Your Lordship.
Thank you.
We're husband and wife -
"thank-you's" are for strangers.
This must be Lord Consort Xian.
I am Meng Jingxian, lord consort of Noble Prince Guo.
Peace to Your Noble Highness.
I wish Your Highness eternal happiness and unending grace.
Please rise.
You were ill on your wedding day
and this is my first time meeting you.
We're a family, there's no need to be so formal.
I should have paid my respects to Your Noble Highness earlier,
but my health hasn't allowed me.
In fact, I came to the palace for two reasons today:
To pay my respects to His Majesty
and to ask forgiveness of Your Highnesses.
Both His Majesty and I have been
thinking about Your Ladyship's health.
Why didn't Yuyin come along
to pay her respects to His Majesty today?
How she's forgotten the rules!
Since Your Ladyship serves His Lordship alongside Yuyin,
please educate her on my behalf
when you have a chance.
Today, the farming estates are reporting their harvest.
Yuyin is attending to it, so she was unable to come.
Yuyin is so skillful with domestic matters.
Unlike me, with my ill health,
I'm only a burden to others.
Your Ladyship's worrying too much.
I heard you're versed in poetry and literature.
How can you be a burden?
Jingxian, don't overthink.
Yuyin is Your Noble Highness's honorary sister.
If Your Noble Highness doesn't mind my dullness,
please see me like a younger sister as well.
Your Lordship overly flatters me.
It's getting late. We shouldn't leave His Majesty waiting.
Aiya! Your Lordship treats Lord Consort Xian so kindly.
No less than how you treat Noble Consort Lumière's sister.
It seems the left- and right-hand consorts
are "equally sharing the spring scenery."
Your Lordship is really a loving husband.
We shall take our leave.
Just after Your Highness arrived,
Her Noble Highness has returned.
It's rare to see you here, Paix.
Does Your Noble Highness always have so many servants around?
You may all leave if not on service.
A cold wind blew through the imperial garden today.
The chill could have entered Your Noble Highness's chest.
Quickly warm it with a sip of tea.
You saw them too?
I've long heard of Lord Consort Xian's devotion.
"Seeing is better than hearing a hundred times."
Where were you hiding to watch that show?
Life is tough. One always has to put on a show.
But within this palace especially,
there are good shows everywhere you go.
So you think Lord Consort Xian
was just putting on an act?
Some acts may appear fake, yet the feelings are true.
Your Highness feels uncomfortable
after seeing only one act of the show.
I wonder how Lord Consort Yu feels
seeing Xian's devotion day after day.
Yuyin is not like that.
Don't underestimate the jealousy in a woman's heart.
Ever since their wedding,
Lord Consort Yu has been the one to
accompany His Lordship to the palace.
But now that Lord Consort Xian has improved her health,
I'm afraid Lord Consort Yu may finally taste neglect
amidst managing all the estate affairs.
She won't.
At the moment, they are on equal footings.
Precisely because of their equal and balanced status,
if His Lordship shows more favor for one,
the neglected one could become narrow-minded and be unable to bear it.
Why His Lordship married Yuyin -
Your Noble Highness knows better than I do.
How could that little portrait
fall out easily for no reason?
His Lordship is not a careless man.
"The wood has been made into a boat."
Concubine Paix, you should understand
one can rely only on what they hold in their two hands.
But you and I
lost the chance to be in Yuyin's position a long time ago.
She acted in her own interest,
but that's understandable.
"Heaven destroys those who don't act in their own interest."
Lord Consort Yu must not lose sight of her conscience.
I'll go back and restore my energy.
I'm sure there are endless good shows to come.
I don't want to miss them.
I'll take my leave.
Does Your Noble Highness know why
all the imperial concubines love to eat sweets?
For the bitterness in their hearts,
sweets are probably the only remedy.
Then Your Highness should eat some more.
There is no need to take Concubine Paix's words to heart.
That's true.
Yuyin will visit the palace in a couple days.
Be sure to prepare her favorite snacks in advance.
Yes.
Noble Lady.
Third Prince.
You should address me the same way as other concubines.
It's just the two of us.
Peace to Your Highness.
- You may go now.
- Yes.
Third Prince, do you have something to tell me?
I added lyrics to your "High Mountain and Flowing Water".
Have you heard my version yet?
Third Prince, please don't talk about that!
If His Majesty knows you are not focused on your studies,
he will scold you again.
I knew it.
In this palace, you're the only one who cares about me.
Only you understand me.
Third Prince, what are you doing?
I am your father's concubine!
You are good to me!
- I don't care about the title or status!
- Stay back!
Am I nothing next to my Imperial Father?!
I have you in my heart!
He's already an old man!
What's going on today?
Noble Lady Lustré looks flustered
and the Third Prince seems as if he's lost his soul.
Their blood and qi are so firey.
I'm afraid they...
No wonder...
I heard the performers rehearsing a lyric version of
Noble Lady Lustré's "High Mountain and Flowing Water."
It seems that the Third Prince ordered it
based on Lady Lustré's melody.
Your Highness is saying...
The Third Prince is the foster son of the Empress.
The Empress is his mother.
This is a serious matter.
Have someone keep an eye out.
Yes.
You've already stayed here for a few days.
His Lordship will worry if you don't return soon.
His Lordship treats Meng Jingxian better than me
and the servants have become snobbish.
I see no point in going back.
Your Highness, Lord Consort Xian is here
from Noble Prince Guo's estate.
She said she wishes to pay respects to Your Highness.
"Speak of Cao Cao and he arrives".
It's true that we can't talk about others behind their back.
Elder sister, I don't want to see her.
I've already seen enough of her fawning over His Lordship.
That's why I'm here - to avoid her and have some quiet!
Why can't I just have some peace?
"What one doesn't see brings one peace."
Go hide over there. I'll handle her.
-Your Highness.
- Show her in.
Peace to Noble Consort Lumière.
Rise.
Have a seat.
What brings you here to visit today?
I came to pay my respects to His Majesty
and decided to visit Your Highness as well.
I heard Yuyin has been staying here for the last few days.
But I don't see her around.
You just missed her; she just left to visit Noble Consort Estime.
She wants to sew some clothes for Princess Longyue.
Yuyin is so fond of children.
Have some tea.
Your Highness's tea is so fragrant.
But my condition makes tea unsuitable for me.
Otherwise, I would love to savor this fine tea.
What's wrong? Is Your Ladyship unwell?
The imperial doctor said
that I am one month pregnant.
My prenatal qi is not stable yet,
so I shouldn't drink tea for now.
This careless maid is new to the palace.
So clumsy she can't even clean a dress rack properly.
Sorry to disturb Your Highness.
What's wrong with you?
Hold the rack up now!
Stop crying. Her Highness and Her Ladyship are out there.
Don't disturb them.
That is wonderful news.
I failed to discipline the maids well.
Please forgive me, Your Ladyship.
New maids are usually careless.
Our estate is orderly all thanks to Yuyin's abilities.
If it was me,
I wouldn't be capable of supervising the servants.
Yuyin is competent, but that doesn't compare
to your contribution of bearing His Lordship's heir.
Since I married into the family,
I have always heard
that His Lordship has loved Yuyin for years.
That was why he married her.
Yuyin is deeply devoted to His Lordship.
Just as Your Ladyship is to His Lordship, as well.
His Lordship has only sympathy towards me.
And I'm the only one who knows
how this pregnancy came about.
Because only with a child
will His Lordship's heart dwell with mine.
But recently I discovered
that Yuyin is also going to great lengths to please His Lordship.
If His Lordship and Yuyin are as deeply in love as everyone says,
why does she need to try so hard to please him?
Since Your Ladyship has married into the family,
I would like to share my years of experience in the harem.
"A suspicious heart brings out ghosts in the dark".
The deeper you think, the more trouble you may cause.
Those who don't overthink are the wise ones.
So I hope.
But I really can't work out what is the truth.
As I said,
you are thinking too much due to your pregnancy.
Now that I share the pillow with His Lordship,
I can see many things that others cannot.
As it should be. This is the nature of marriage.
I should take my leave.
Meng Jingxian is too smart.
One day her suspicions will harm His Lordship.
She loves His Lordship deeply.
She will put his well-being first.
But now she is pregnant with His Lordship's child,
where is there room for me in the estate?
Meng Jingxian's unborn child
is His Lordship's rightful heir.
You are the child's mother in name.
Of course there is room for you.
You are the second daughter of our Niohuru family,
and the lord consort of Noble Prince Guo.
Your virtue should befit your status.
I love His Lordship deeply
and I will naturally treat his child well.
But Elder Sister,
my heart is bitter.
What happened in the past is of no importance.
The present is what matters.
His Majesty holds Meng Jingxian in high regard
and this is the firstborn to the estate.
You ought to take good care of her,
and let no harm come to her.
"I shall be known and loved by you"
"long without decay or an end."
["By Heaven" from Shijing]
"I shall be known and loved by you"
"long without decay or an end."
Third Prince,
I've been hearing you reciting these lines for days now.
Xiao-Lezi,
am I unworthy?
Quite the opposite. Why?
You are the pride of Heaven.
What's the point of being Heaven's pride?
There is only one person
who cares about me.
Who?
Look, words are filling up my heart and lungs
but I don't know how to tell them to her.
Master, if you can't speak, why not write?
Aren't you clever!
What did your Imperial Mother summon you for?
Imperial Mother said now that I've come of age,
Father will arrange a marriage for me.
The girl surnamed Fuca is a fine lady.
I have faith in her.
I trust your judgment, Mother.
But I am still young, and having a primary wife will be enough.
Yet Imperial Mother wishes me to also take
the lady surnamed Ula-Nara as my lord consort.
Mother, have you heard she is...
I know it all.
Since Her Majesty requested, you should agree.
There's no need to offend her over a trifle.
But she was rejected by my third brother.
Assigning her to me...
The Third Prince rejected her, but you will accommodate her.
That only shows your generosity.
Your brother's willful action will now do you a favor.
She will be merely a lord consort.
Just marry her and keep her well provided for at home.
No one is asking you to bow like a maid and serve her.
Yes.
If you really dislike Qingying,
I have one more candidate in mind.
The lady surnamed Gao who's been taking care of you -
She's gentle and virtuous.
I also know that you like her.
Wait a couple years
and I will request His Majesty
to decree her to be your Lord Consort.
Mother, you've been thinking for me.
I understand the bigger picture
and won't make things difficult for Mother.
That's good.
Peace to Your Highness.
Please rise.
His Majesty invites Your Highness
to the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
I will leave right away.
Peace and grace to Your Majesties.
What is going on?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.